Guide to the Henry Geldzahler Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Henry Geldzahler papers
1945-2006
YCAL MSS 684
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
43.54
(51 boxes) + 14 cold storage
The Henry Geldzahler papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, audiotapes, video recordings, motion picture film, printed material, and other papers that relate to the personal and professional life of the American photographer Henry Geldzahler. Other papers include notes and writings on Andy Warhol and others, working illustrations and notes for his unfinsished monograph, "Modern Art in America", and footage used in Peter Rosen's 2005 documentary about Geldzahler, Who Gets To Call It Art ?. The material documents Geldzahler's career as a curator of contemporary art, his relationships with artists, and his involvement in the art world of the 1960s and 1970s.
Geldzahler, Henry, 1935-1994
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jonathan Geldzahler and Annette Banton, 1999; Jonathan Geldzahler, 2007; Peter Rosen, 2008; and the Metropolitan Museum of Art, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 2, 14, 21-25, 44-50 (audiocassettes, videocassettes, CDs, and DVDs): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Box 51 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Reels 52-65 (motion picture film): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Henry Geldzahler (1935-1994)
Henry Geldzahler was born in Antwerp, Belgium in 1935, and emigrated with his family to the United States in 1940. He graduated from Yale University in 1957 and joined the staff of The Metropolitan Museum of Art in 1960, becoming the first curator of contemporary art. In 1966, Geldzahler served as United States Commissioner of Art at the Venice Biennale, as well as the first director of the Visual Arts program for the National Endowment for the Arts. From 1977 to 1982, he held the position of Cultural Affairs Commissioner for the City of New York. After leaving that job, he worked as a private curator. Geldzahler died of cancer in 1994.
Scope and Contents
The Henry Geldzahler papers consist of correspondence, writings, photographs, audiotapes, video recordings, motion picture film, computer disks, printed material, and other papers that relate to the personal and professional life of the American photographer Henry Geldzahler. Other papers include notes and writings on Andy Warhol and others, working illustrations and notes for his unfinsished monograph, "Modern Art in America", and footage used in Peter Rosen's 2005 documentary about Geldzahler, Who Gets To Call It Art ?. The material documents Geldzahler's career as a curator of contemporary art, his relationships with artists, and his involvement in the art world of the 1960s and 1970s.
Arrangement
Organized into four groupings: I. December 1999 Acquisition, circa 1945-1996. II. November 2007 Acquisition, circa 1994-2004. III. June 2008 Acquisition, 2005-2006. IV. October 2009 Acquisition, 1994.
Material within this collection has been organized by acquisition reflecting the fact that the collection has been acquired in increments over time.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with and/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers will need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
Researchers should also note that similar material can be arranged differently in each acquisition, depending on how the material was organized when it was received by the library.
Art, American -- 20th Century; Art museum curators -- United States; Art, Modern -- 20th Century; Painting, American -- 20th Century; Sculpture, American -- 20th Century; Audiotapes; Audiovisual materials; Born digital; Motion pictures (visual works); Photographs; Videotapes; Art museum curators -- United States -- 20th Century; Geldzahler, Henry, 1935-1994; Warhol, Andy, 1928-1987; Metropolitan Museum of Art (New York, N.Y.)
- December 1999 Acquisition, circa 1945-1996; 1; 39.04; (43 boxes)
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of Jonathan Geldzahler and Annette Banton, 1999.
  General note
  The donor's original folder numbering has been retained. This numbering system varies throughout the acquisition.
  Scope and Contents
  This acquisition consists of correspondence, writings, photographs, sound and video recordings, and printed material, by or relating to Henry Geldzahler. Includes notes and writings on Andy Warhol and others; and working illustrations and notes for Modern Art in America.
  Former call number: Uncat MSS 30.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Boxes 2, 14, 21-25 (audiocassettes and CDs): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 51 (computer disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies of electronic files may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  - "Determining Aesthetic Values in Art": 27 pages legal size xerox of manuscript with editor's emendations in pencil; 25 pages handwritten notes for above (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Two Lectures: "Soho; Past & Future" Lecture delivered May 15, 1975 at Artist's Space, NYC; 21 page Xerox of typescript; "Art in Public Places," 12 page handwritten notes (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - "Selected Writings 1985-86" (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Approximately 100-page paste-up (assembled by Geldzahler) of xeroxes containing: 1) Pop Art 1955-70; 2) Rosenquist's studio; 3) Clemente prints; 4) I. M. Pei interview; 5) Steven Buckley; 6) Andrew Lord; 7) Jules and Doris Stein collection; 8) Noguchi; 9) Miami; 10) Dennis Hopper; 11) Chihuly; 12) Arman.
  - Francesco Clemente: approximately 150 pages of manuscript, typescript, and lecture notes and transcripts (in RF's hand) with heavy emendations in Geldzahler's hand in red and black ink. Final essay published in "F. C: Frescos" Madrid: 1987, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Five Lectures, 1963-1966 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    1) "An Examination of Art Education", 54-page carbon typescript with author's corrections, July 1966. 2) "USIA Lecture" current overview of US art and artists, 1965, 14-page carbon typescript. 3) "Origins and Early Development of Ab. Art", 1963, 26-page original typescript with author's corrections. 4) "Mod. Europe Painting and Sculpture", circa 1963, 20 page original typescript with author corrections. 5) "Recent Developments [in Art]", Metropolitan Museum lecture, February 1963, 25 page original typescript.
  - de Kooning: 5 page typescript and paste-up with author corrections, circa 1988 on de Kooning paintings, 1956-62, published in catalogue by Gagosian Gallery, NYC (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Wallace Putnam, circa 1986, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    1) 4 typescript letters signed by WP. Numerous gallery announcement cards; 2) One catalogue, miscellaneous photos and clippings, plus 6 original typescripts with paste-up plus emendations in hand. circa 1986; 3) 26 page xerox of typescript. "Rothko Seen Again" a sort of memoir by Putnam, unpublished; 4) Artist's biography plus supplementary material on an overlooked American painter, contemporary and friend to Rothko and Avery.
  - Geldzahler Biography: Approximately 12 page typescript and Xerox of typed biographical entries and vita on Geldzahler (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Warhol: Xerox of 3 articles on AW by Geldzahler with some author's emendations, 1964-1987 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    1) AW: Swedish Museum catalog intro 1964; 2) "Some Notes on Sleep" Film Culture 1964; 3) Obit for British Vogue; 4) Some press reviews of an AW show curated by Geldzahler in Bridgehampton, NY, circa 1987.
  - "Hans Hoffman", lecture, 29 pages. Xerox of typescript with some author corrections in hand, 1976 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dale Chihuly: Glass artist, circa 1985, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
    1) 3 page typescript with author corrections "DC at the Louvre" circa 1985; 2) 13 page Xerox typescript with author and editor's (RF) notes: Chihuly discussing his career with Geldzahler; 3) 6 pages Xerox typescript of essay on DC; 4) 5 pages handwritten notes on DC; 5) 1 page signed letter typed to Geldzahler from DC; 6) Press clip on Chihuly from Seattle Times.
  - Jack Whitten: Approximately 100-page file of notes, manuscript, typescript, letters plus from this contemporary black American artist. Various catalogues and press clips circa 1983 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Pop Art/Museum of Modern Art: Approximately 150 page file including notes, manuscript, typescript, letters, checklist, artist's biography etc. Working materials for Pop Art Show organized for The Museum of Modern Art in 1986-1987, circa 1986 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - NY Painting and Sculpture: Approximately 200 pages typescript and carbon and Xeroxes of artist's exhibition histories for exhibition at Met Museum 1969 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Keith Haring: Xerox of 6 page typescript of essay "Art in Transit", Clarkson Potter, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Larry Stanton: 5 pages original manuscript with corrections in author's hand on young figure painter died of AIDS, circa 1988. Published in a catalogue by Twelvetrees Books (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National Endowment for the Arts: 1 page Xerox of proposal to NEA on purchasing works by living artists, titled by Geldzahler: "Preamble to challenge grant in support of living artists and/or purchasing or presenting their art." (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Noguchi: 7 page original manuscript with author corrections in hand: intro to catalogue essay; 23 page Xerox of typescript of unpublished interview with Noguchi; 5 page typescript of #1 with heavy emendations by editor (RF) (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "History of Art in 3000 Slides" 2 versions of a 2 page typescript proposal, submitted to American Society, 1986. A proposal for a master 3,000 slide library on the art of the Americas (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Miami: Approximately 20 pages of manuscript, typescript with author's emendations on art and architecture of Miami Beach, Florida (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Dorothea Tanning: Approximately 40 pages of manuscript notes, original manuscript, original typescript with author corrections, an unpublished interview, and typescript letter signed from D. Tanning, 1986 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Ideas and Topics: 4 pages Xerox typescript proposal to Hearst Corp. on American Art and Design, 1887-1987 with a few author's emendations, plus nine other topics proposed for Hearst publication articles (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Noguchi: 20 page handwritten notes, typescript and letter and budget proposal concerning the 1986 Venice Biennale curated by Geldzahler. Includes the original USIA proposal of Noguchi for V.B., 1984 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - National Endowment for the Arts: 35 page history of NEA by graduate student John Pultz - quotes and mentions Geldzahler extensively. Typescript letter signed by J.P. to Geldzahler (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Jules & Doris Stein: 5 pages Galleys to House and Garden article on Jules and Doris Stein collection (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Warhol: 8 page handwritten notes on Warhol as obituary for British Vogue (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - "6 Young Unknown Artists": 2 page original typescript with author corrections, for exhibition at DIA Art Foundation in Bridgehampton, NY, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - NY Paintings and Sculpture, 1940-1970: Approximately 80 pages manuscript and typescript of Bibliographical material included in Metropolitan Museum catalogue (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - "America Looks to Europe": article for Architecture Digest magazine; 11 page legal size handwritten notes; 6 pages original typescript with author corrections (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Hockney: Approximately 50 pages of manuscript notes and typescript with paste up and author notes to an essay on Hockney's portraits (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Noguchi: 2 page original typescript with notes: "Thoughts on Sculpture." 20 page typescript of essay by Geldzahler: Noguchi: Life and Art (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - The Artist & Urban Space: 26 page typescript; 13 page original typed lecture notes with author emendations for Copley Square Boston Redevelopment Authority, 1983 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Alice Neel: 3 page manuscript notes - Questions for Alice Neel. 50 page (approximate) typed interview: 4 versions with various editorial and authors emendations (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - George Baselitz: 27 pages xerox typescript of interview with, published in Interview magazine (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - I.M. Pei: 20 page heavily edited and pasted interviews with I.M. Pei on Louvre revisions. Published in Elle magazine, circa 1987 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Ray Johnson: 3 letters, 1985 July - August (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Rainbow Room: A file of notes, 3 page proposal, slides, photos and miscellaneous catalogues for the Rainbow Room of Rockefeller Center, circa 1988. Geldzahler was artistic consultant to renovation of the Rainbow Room. (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Mary Boone: 2 versions of a 16 page interview with art dealer Mary Boone, heavily edited by author and editor (RF) (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - The Gallery Scene and other essays: a lecture delivered by Geldzahler at the Metropolitan Museum on NY gallery scene. Original typescript with notes and paste ups; xeroxes of 2 other essays on related subject, and the influence of criticism on contemporary art, circa 1963 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - The Southampton Pres: A file of approximately 6 press clippings on Geldzahler from circa 1988, concerning Geldzahler's memorial exhibition on Warhol at the Bridgehampton DIA foundation (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Press Notices: Another file of press clips, photos and press release from 1964 (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Miscellaneous Essays (Box 1, Folder 42)
    1) Typescript of "Twenty Stories for John Cage", 3 pages with author corrections: very amusing art world anecdotes; 2) 4 pages xeroxed typescript with hand notations on "Underknowns" exhibition a P.S. 1 circa 1987; 3) 11 page typescript of interview with Jean Michel Basquiat, published in Interview magazine The complete interview, prior to JMB's radical editing; 4) June 5, 1976 School for Visual Arts, NYC, commencement address: Xeroxed typescript with penciled notes.
  - Memos to James Rorimer: xerox typescript of 8 page memo to Director of the Metropolitan Museum, James Rorimer, on the future need for planning a Department of 20th Century Art at the Metropolitan Museum; written in 1964. This "policy paper" outlines what Geldzahler sought to accomplish as the Met's first curator of 20th art (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Edie Sedgwick: 20 page single spaced carbon of unpublished interview by Jean Stein with Geldzahler on the subject of Edie Sedgwick, for her oral biography "Edie" with George Plimpton. An extensive account of Geldzahler's role and view of the Warhol scene in the 1960s and early 70s, his mixed feelings about AW, and his continued contact with ES until the weeks prior to her death (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Op-Ed Pieces: 9 page original typescript with author corrections for the NY Times on the subject of being NYC Commissioner of Cultural Affairs, unpublished (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - Miscellaneous Notes: Confidential memo to Fred Hughes on direction of Andy Warhol Foundation; Approximately 15 handwritten legal pages - lecture notes for "Public Art" delivered at the Tel Aviv Museum circa 1987 - unpublished (Box 1, Folder 46)
  - Stephen Buckley: approximately 15 pages original typescript with author notes and paste ups for an essay on the English abstract artist (Box 1, Folder 47)
  - Domenico Paulon: approximately 40 pages of notes, typescript, letters, etc. relating to exhibition and catalogue of this Italian-American abstract pioneer (Box 1, Folder 48)
  - Miscellaneous Essays, 1966-1982 (Box 1, Folder 49)
    1) Determining Esthetic Values in Art, 22 page original typescript with pen corrections. 2 Xerox copies of same; 2) Archives of American Art Journal, Vol. 22 #1, 1982. Copy of Journal. "Adventures with Bolatowsky" by Geldzahler on page 8; 3) Interview with Philip Johnson. 15 page Xerox, dated 4/1/82. For Interview magazine, rejected by P. J. perhaps because of questions about architect's interest in German National Socialism of late 1920s; 4) Taste But Not 'Good' Taste, 3 page Xerox circa 1980; 5) John McKendry: In Memoriam, 4 page Xerox of clean typescript 1974. A memoir of the Met's curator of prints and drawings; 6) Is New York Losing Its Stuarts: 1 page essay Xeroxed from Soho Weekly News, 4/19/79; 7) Preface: 2 page Xerox of essay on Bruce Johnson's work. August 1978; 8) Career and The Artist: 4 page Xerox with hand notations. circa 1979; 9) Needed: Inexpensive Hotels Here. 1 page Xerox of essay appearing in The NY Times, October 3, 1979; 10) Irving Penn: Street Material. 1 page tract for show; 11) George Segal: 12 page Xerox from Quadrum No. 19, 1966.
  - Miscellaneous Essays (Box 1, Folder 50)
    1) Recent Accessions - Twentieth Century Art. 20 page Xerox copy of hand corrected typescript. 1974; 2) Pop Art. 2 page Xerox from Art News, Vol. 73, No. 5, May 1974 with felt pen notation; 3) Collage by Joseph Cornell. 1 page Xerox from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, Vol. XXIX, No. 4, December 1970, page 152; 4) Jean Arpage 7 page Xerox, 1972; 5) New York Painting and Sculpturegarding 1940-1970. 38 page Xerox with hand notation; 6) Art Education Today. Transcription of lecture given at Grinell University, Iowa, 1968. 19 original typescript with hand notations; 7) James Rosenquist's F-111. 6 page Xerox from Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, Vol. XXVI, No. 7, March 1968; 8) Interview with Frank Stella. 6 page Xerox of hand corrected typescript, 1966; 9) 1 page press release (Xerox) for the Venice Biennale. June 14, 1966; 10) Frankenthaler, Kelly, Lichtenstein, Olitski. 5 page Xerox from Art Forum, Vol. IV, No. 10, page 32-8, July 1966; 11) George Segal. 4 page Xerox from recent American Sculpture, The Jewish Museum, New York, October 15-November 29, 1964; 12) Interview with Ellsworth Kelly. 7 page Xerox. 1963; 13) Interview with Larry Poons. 5 page Xerox of hand corrected original typescript. 1963; 14) 5 page Xerox of original hand corrected typescript - subject: The Metropolitan Museum; commitment to 20th Century art. 1964; 15) Two Early Matisse Drawings. 9 page Xerox. published 1962, written 1959; 16) Parochial World News. 3 page Xerox from Art News, Vol. 60, No. 9, 1962 (January); 17) Edward Hopper. 5 page Xerox from Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, November 1962; 18) Heller: New American-type collector. 4 page Xerox from Art News, Vol. 60, No. 5, September 1961; 19) Numbers in Time: Two American Paintings. 5 page Xerox from The Metropolitan Museum of Art Bulletin, Vol. XXIII, No. 8, April, 1965; 20) Chapter Seven - Neo-Classicism, Nationalism and The Depression. The Inter-War Years. 24 page Xerox of hand corrected typescript.From "Modern Art in America." (unpublished); 21) Xeroxed articles on Chicago Arts Club (Not by Geldzahler). Sent by James N. Wood with letter.
  - Modern Art in America: An extensive manuscript left nearly finished at the time of his death, circa 1985-1986 (Box 2, Folder 51)
    1) 61 page typescript; 2) 30 page typescript of Preface and Chapter 1, with numerous corrections in red ink in author's hand; 3) 26 page working draft of above, heavily edited and pasted-up by the author; 4) 40 page typescript with heavy editing in the author's hand: discussion of topics to be addressed in the book.
  - Modern Art in America. Chapter 5-7 working copies, heavily corrected in author's hand; some typescript, a few xeroxed pages, many paste-ups, approximately 150 pages (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - An Examination of Art Education. 54 page Xerox of hand corrected typescript, 1966 July (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - 2 Lectures: 1) Cross-Pollination: European and American Art. 27 page Xerox of typed transcription from lecture at the Whitney Museum of American Art. 2) European Sources of American Art. 22 page Xerox of heavily corrected typed transcription of lecture at Phoenix Art Museum, February 22, 1984, 1984, undated (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Modern Art in America: xeroxes of working drafts. Chapters 2 and 3 plus letter from (editor) Jane Isay at Simon-Schuster (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Miscellaneous notes: by Geldzahler, all handwritten on legal paper, 1983-1988 (Box 2, Folder 56)
    1) 2 pages: "Arts in NYC"; 2) 14 pages: NYPL lecture "Underground Art" 1/19/88; 3) 5 pages on Warhol for Sotheby's AW estate sale; 4) 12 pages, further notes on NYPL lecture 1/19/88, here titled "The Audience for New Art," notes dated 12/24/87; 5) 8 pages notes on hanging a show of Geldzahler's personal collection, at the Century Association gallery, NYC; 6) 10 pages in someone else's hand, with Geldzahler's notes. A chart of comparative illustrations for a lecture at the Lowe Art Museum 2/9/83 [see file #57 for lecture transcript]; 7) 4 pages, notes on a lecture about his career as Curator at Museum of Modern Art, delivered in San Diego.
  - Lecture, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 57)
    1) 30 original typescript with corrections from lecture 2/9/83 for Friends of Art, Lowe Art Museum; 2) Handwritten thank you card from Elaine Goldman; 3) Miscellaneous press clippings and P. R. pamphlets.
  - Underknowns: approximately 125 page file including notes, manuscript, typescript, letters, artist's biographies etc. for "Underknown" show curated at P.S. I, October 14th-December 9, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 58)
    Artists included Gandy Brodie, Bob Thompson, Frank Auerbach, Eugene LeRoy, Walter Murch, David Park, Anne Ryan, John McLaughlin, Sally Drummond, Domenico Paulon, Ernie Briggs
  - Auerbach, Frank: approximately 30 page file of xeroxed articles on F.A. plus 8 photographs of paintings (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Briggs, Ernie: 8x10 color card announcement for exhibition, 1984 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Brodie, Gandy: Catalogue, press clippings and 5 color Polaroids (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Drummond, Sally Hazelet: 5 Xerox pages of info on artist (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Leroy, Eugene: catalogue from Michael Werner in Koln Show, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Muller, Jan: 15 page file - all xeroxes - including artist biography and essays on artist plus artwork and notes (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Murch, Walter: 1) 46 pages xerox transcribed interview with artist and interviewer Arlene Jocobowitz; 2) B&W photograph, 6x10 of painting Moon Rock; 3) 5 page xeroxes of photographed paintings; 4) 12 page reviews of exhibitions (xerox copies) (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - McLauchlin, John: 1 page xerox biographical info. on artist; 1 page original typed with hand corrections essay on artist (unfinished) (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Park, David: 1) Two 8x10 color catalogues from Maxwell Galleries, August 14-September 26, 1970 exhibition; 2) 34 pages xerox reviews of exhibitions and chronology; 3) 2 miscellaneous typed notes regarding artist (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Ryan, Anne: approximately 40 xerox pages - reviews, biographical information, etc. (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Thompson, Bob: approximately 20 xerox pages: biography, review, etc.; 3 page article from Art in America, May 1983, with color photographs, 1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence: approximately 80 pages personal and business correspondence and replies to Geldzahler including (galleries, office of the mayor of NY), 1982 and 1983. Plus xeroxes of letters from Geldzahler to Jay Islin, Jacqueline Onassis, Sotheby's etc., mostly declining various job offers following his commissionership, 1982-1983, undated (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Miscellaneous, 1983 (Box 2, Folder 71)